Partial Register of the N. V. Borzov Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
- N.V.Borzov material at the Museum of Russian Culture (Reel 1-36)
  - SUBJECT FILE, 1918-1984 (Box 13-31)
    - Ob"edinennyi komitet russkikh natsional'nykh organizatsii. (Box 19)
      Clippings, correspondence, financial statements and other material relating to the activities of N. V. Borzov as director/president of this organization
      - General, 1926-1947 (Folder 19: 1)
        Appeals, circulars, membership lists, financial documents, notes, minutes of meetings, reports, and other records
      - Clippings about the Ob"edinennyi komitet (Folder 19: 2)
      - Correspondence, 1928-1947 and undated (Folder 19: 3)
      - Founding documents (Folder 19: 4)
    - Obshchestvo pokrovitel'stva i prosveshcheniia russkikh detei (Society for Protection and Education of Russian Children).
      See also Den' russkago rebenka for this organization's participation in the celebration. N. V. Borzov was this organization's director and principal of and a teacher in the evening school
      - General
        - General. (Folder 19: 5)
          Includes correspondence, financial statements, memoranda, notes, and other materials
        - By-laws (Folder 19: 6)
      - Russkaia vecherniaia gimnaziia (Russian Evening School)
        - General. (Folder 19: 7-8)
          Includes attendance rolls, notes, memoranda, programs of school events and graduation ceremonies, teachers' reports, schedules, and other school records
        - General (Box-folder 20: 1-3)
        - Clippings (Folder 20: 4)
        - Correspondence
          - General (Folder 20: 5)
          - Letters from parents, 1943 and undated (Folder 20: 6)
        - Course materials. (Folder 20: 7)
          Assignments, lecture notes for Borzov's courses on history, geography and literature, and similar matter
        - Course materials (Box-folder 21: 1-2)
        - Diplomas (Folder 21: 3)
        - Financial records. (Folder 21: 4)
          Receipts and receipt books
        - Library records (Folder 21: 5)
        - Report cards. (Folder 21: 6)
          See also General for grades affixed to other documents
        - Students' works (Box-folder 22: 1-4)
      - Russkii detskii sad (Russian Day Nursery)
        - General. (Folder 22: 5)
          Includes materials and fragments of writings for a history of the kindergarten over 20 years of its existence (1925-1945)
        - Clippings, 1927-1947 (Folder 22: 6)
        - Correspondence, 1927-1945 and undated (Folder 22: 7)
        - Facilities record book (Box-folder 23: 1)
        - Financial records, 1927-1946 (Folder 23: 2)
        - Programs of fundraising events (Folder 23: 3)
    - Obshchestvo prepodavatelei russkago iazyka.
      Includes papers of the Komitet po vvedeniiu russkogo iazyka v amerikanskikh uchebnykh zavedeniiakh. N. V. Borzov was this organization's founder and director
      - General. (Folder 23: 4)
        Includes correspondence, memoranda, minutes of meetings, notes
      - Clippings (Folder 23: 5)
      - Untitled Russian language study guide compiled by N. V. Borzov, n.d. (Folder 23: 6)
        Holograph
    - Obshchestvo russkikh veteranov Velikoi voiny, San Francisco, California (Folder 23: 7)
    - Pasternak, Boris, Articles about (Folder 23: 8)
    - Pedagogicheskii institut, Harbin, China. (Folder 23: 9)
      Correspondence, memoranda, leaflets and other records
    - 1-oe [i.e., Pervoe] Kharbinskoe russkoe real'noe uchilishche. (Folder 23: 10-11)
      See also BIOGRAPHICAL FILE/Addresses for addresses honoring Borzov for his activities in this capacity, and MEMORABILIA for plaque and diagrams of the school
      Clippings, correspondence, notes, programs and other materials relating primarily to N. V. Borzov's term as principal of this school, 1929-1931.
    - Pushkin, Aleksandr Sergeevich. (Box-folder 24)
      See also CORRESPONDENCE/Pushkin Society in America
      Materials relating to celebrations in his honor, organized or with the participation of N. V. Borzov, in 1937 and 1949.
      - General. (Folder 24: 1-2)
        Announcements, memoranda, lists, reports, and similar matter
      - Clippings (Folder 24: 3)
      - Correspondence
        - 1935-1938 (Folder 24: 4)
        - 1947-1949 (Folder 24: 5)
      - Financial records (Folder 24: 6)
      - Miscellany. (Folder 24: 7)
        Periodical issues, programs, and other printed matter
    - Rakitin, Sergei S. Clippings (Box-folder 25: 1)
    - Refugees, Russian. (Folder 25: 2)
      Correspondence and bulletins, relating primarily to Russian displaced persons in Europe and the Far East, following the Second World War
    - Russian Children's Welfare Society, Inc.
      N. V. Borzov was a member of the California Branch of this organization. For this organization's involvement in the celebrations of Den' russkogo rebenka, see also Den' russkogo rebenka and OVERSIZE FILE/Russian Children's Welfare Society
      - General
        - Annual reports (Folder 25: 3-4)
        - Appeals (Folder 25: 5)
        - Booklet-- Obshchestvo pomoshchi russkim dietiam za rubezhom,: Kratkii istoricheskii ocherk dieiatel'nosti obshchestva, New York, 1951 (Folder 25: 6)
        - By-laws (Folder 25: 7)
        - Clippings (Folder 25: 8)
        - Scrapbooks.
          See OVERSIZE FILE
        - Miscellany (Folder 25: 9)
      - California branch.
        - General. (Folder 25: 10)
          Includes notes, lists of names, etc.
        - Correspondence.
          Letters addressed primarily to N. V. Borzov and A. A. Maksimova-Kulaeva and E. A. Zhelten, president and secretary of the California branch, respectively, relating to aid to Russian children, adoptions, etc. from a variety of correspondents
          - General
            - General, 1936-1946 (Folder 25: 11)
            - Letters from displaced persons in Europe seeking aid for their children, 1947-1948 (Box-folder 26: 1)
          - Borzov, N. V., 1945-1950 (Folder 26: 2)
            See also Den' russkogo rebenka/ Correspondence/Alekseeva, Elizaveta Vital'evna for letters from the latter as representative of the Russian Children's Welfare Society relating to Den' russkogo rebenka celebrations
          - Maksimova-Kulaeva, Antonina Aleksandrovna, 1946-1947 (Folder 26: 3)
            See also Kulaev (Koulaieff) family for other letters to her
          - Zhelten (Jelten), Elena Andreevna, 1946 (Folder 26: 4)
        - Financial records, 1936-1946 (Folder 26: 5)
    - Russian Community School and Library in Berkeley, California (Russkaia obshchestvennaia shkola i biblioteka v Berklee).
      N. V. Borzov was the school principal and a teacher
      - General
        - General (Folder 26: 6-8)
        - School Christmas celebrations, 1932-1933 (Box-folder 27: 1)
      - Correspondence (official). (Folder 27: 2)
        See also Students' works for students' letters to Borzov Financial records
        - General (Folder 27: 3-4)
        - Receipt books (Folder 27: 5)
      - Report cards (Folder 27: 6)
      - Students' works. (Folder 27: 7)
        Includes students' letters to N. V. Borzov
    - Russian Women's Home of Mercy, San Francisco, California. (Folder 27: 8)
      Clippings and invitations
    - Russians
      - China
        - General. (Folder 27: 9)
        - Harbin.
          See also SUBJECT FILE/Chinese Eastern Railway
          - General. (Folder 27: 10)
            Clippings and papers relating to the functioning of the Russian municipal authority and bulletins of the Biuro po delam rossiiskoi emigratsii v Man'chzhurskoi imperii
          - Education. (Folder 28: 2)
            Correspondence, reports and other records of Russian educational institutions in Harbin. For papers of various educational institutions in Harbin that Borzov was affiliated with, see also Institut Iapono-russkogo obshchestva, Khristianskii soiuz molodykh liudei, Pedagogicheskii institut and 1-oe [i.e., Pervoe] Kharbinskoe russkoe real'noe uchilishche
      - Foreign countries. (Folder 28: 3)
      - United States. (Folder 28: 4-6)
        See also Russkaia Pravoslavnaia Tserkov'--United States
        Clippings, brochures, leaflets, periodical issues and photographs of an anti-Communist demonstration.
    - Russkaia Pravoslavnaia Tserkov'--United States. (Folder 29: 2)
      See also Komissiia po bor'be s religioznymi presledovaniiami i razrusheniem khramov v SSSR and Holy Trinity Cathedral for additional material on the Church in the Soviet Union and in San Francisco, as well as PRINTED MATTER/Journals, for individual church and religious bulletins
      Bulletins, clippings and other matter relating to the activities of the Church outside Russia.
    - Russkii klub, San Francisco, California (Folder 29: 3)
    - Russkii muzhskoi khor, San Francisco, California. (Folder 29: 4)
      Clippings and photographs
    - Russkii tsentr (Russian Center), San Francisco, California
      - General. (Folder 29: 5)
        Correspondence, financial records, invitations
      - Clippings (Folder 29: 6)
    - Russkii universitetskii klub.
      San Francisco, California
      - General (Folder 29: 7)
      - Correspondence (Folder 29: 8)
      - Founding documents (Folder 29: 9)
      - Membership records (Folder 29: 10)
      - Miscellany. (Folder 29: 11)
        Papers relating to special events: lectures, concerts, etc.
    - Russko-amerikanskii soiuz zashchity i pomoshchi russkim vne Rossii, New York, New York. (Box-folder 30: 1)
      Clippings and leaflets
    - Russko-amerikanskoe obshchestvo, San Francisco, California. (Folder 30: 2)
      Clippings, leaflets and notes
    - St. John the Baptist Church, Berkeley, California (Tserkov' sv. Ioanna Krestitelia).
      Primarily consists of the papers of V. N. Borzov, who served on the parish council.
      - Bulletins (Folder 30: 3)
      - Correspondence (Folder 30: 4)
      - Financial records (Folder 30: 5)
      - Lists of parishioners and other Russians living nearby (Folder 30: 6)
      - Minutes of meetings of the parish council. (Folder 30: 7)
        Includes activity report, 1939-1940
      - Miscellany. (Folder 30: 8)
        Includes schedules of church services and religious printed matter
    - Soviet Union--History
      - ., 1925-1953 (Folder 30: 9-10)
        Clippings and typed transcripts of intercepted radio messages from Khabarovsk, 1940
      - ., 1953-1985 (Folder 30: 11)
    - Tolstoy, Leo. (Folder 30: 12)
      Clippings, correspondence, financial records, notes and other materials relating to a celebration in his honor, 1935
    - Tolstoy Foundation, New York (Folder 30: 13)
    - World War, --Russia--Veterans, 1914-1918 (Box 31)
      - General. (Folder 31: 1)
        Correspondence, financial records, reports and other documentation concerning N. V. Borzov's involvement in charitable activities to aid Russian military invalids abroad
      - Clippings (Folder 31: 2)
    - Miscellany (Folder 31: 3-5)
  - PRINTED MATTER, 1902-1969
    Books, journals, newspapers and programs, arranged alphabetically by physical form. Includes rare pre-Revolutionary Russian periodicals, such as issues of Libavskiia birzhevyia izviestiia (Libava, 1910), Taganrogskii viestnik (Taganrog, 1902), and Viestnik uchashchikhsia (Vladivostok, 1917), as well as periodicals issued outside Russia, such as Novaia zhizn' (Harbin, 1917) and V dobryi chas (Italy, 1950-1954). Also well represented are émigré religious periodicals
    - Books (Folder 31: 6)
    - Journals (Box-folder 32: 1-5)
    - Newspapers (Box-folder 33: 1-2)
    - Programs (Folder 33: 3-5)
  - OVERSIZE FILE, 1921-1973 (Box 34)
    Ledgers, scrapbooks and miscellany, arranged alphabetically by name of organization
    - Russian Children's Welfare Society. (Folder 34: 1-4)
      Scrapbooks
    - Russkoe natsional'noe studencheskoe obshchestvo
      - Ledgers (Folder 34: 5)
      - Membership records (Folder 34: 6)
      - Scrapbook (Folder 34: 7)
    - Miscellany (Folder 34: 8)
  - MEMORABILIA, n.d. (Box-folder 35: 1-2)
    Plaque and diagrams of the 1-oe Kharbinskoe russkoe real'noe uchilishche
  - PHOTOGRAPHS, n.d.
    One album and fifteen prints depicting miscellaneous personages. See also SUBJECT FILE/Russians--United
    - Album (Folder 35: 3)
    - Prints. (Folder 35: 4)
      Fifteen prints depicting miscellaneous personages, including V. P. Kulaev and S. P. Kovalev